Today I will introduce to you how to load model 3D by OpenGL
As you see here, I have loaded a tree model
I can use left mouse to rotate
And middle mouse to zoom in/out
Actually these models are made up of an infinite number of triangles
Or quads
These faces will be stitched together
The more faces the model has
The more realistic the model will be
Now, I will draw a cube by OpenGL
A cube consists of 8 vertices
And 6 faces
Based on the following coordinate system
The vertices v0 to v7 will have the coordinates shown in the figure
To draw this cube, I need to keep a complete list of vertices
Also show the faces of the cube
Are made of which vertices
First, face 0 includes vertex 0, 1, 2, 3
Additional, I need save the normal vector of the face
The main use case for normal vectors are lighting calculations
The brightness of the faces will depend on normal vectors
Similar to the other faces
Yeah, Let's code
To load Wavefront .obj file, of course we need fstream, you can use stdio too
We will have to use some additional libraries like vector to store the list, math for calculation
Freeglut for OpenGL, and glext to initialize screen in antialiasing mode
Some libraries load pictures I write
Turn on light, use only 1 light, LIGHT0
Set position of the light
Background color is gray
Set default coordinates by matrix projection
And turn on some beauty modes, 3D
Turn on depth test make OpenGL renders model depend on depth
The things that were ahead obscure the things that were behind
Display function, clear screen first
Main function
Multisample to set the anti-aliasing mode
Ok, run
Now, I will draw a cube
First, declare 8 vertices of the cube
Next, 6 normal vectors of the cube
And 6 faces of the cube, each face includes 4 vertices
Draw 6 faces by glBegin POLYGON
4 vertices of the polygon correspond to each vertex declared above
Ok, render the cube successfully
Next, I will define the model by a class
Each model includes many faces, so I create a class Face inside
Each face has a number of edges, references to vertices, normal vectors